A Guide to the National Committee on United States-China Relations records, RG 9, Accession 9 FA1191
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Programs, Projects, and Proposals, 1968-2001; 8; 6.39 Cubic Feet
  - Luce Foundation Civil Society Project - Proposal, 1997 (Box 21, Folder 209)
    Proposal for funding of the "Three Revolutions Project," 1998-2000. In December 1997, the Henry Luce Foundation approved a three-year grant of $300,000 in support of a public education and exchange program on decentralization, privatization, and civic organizations in China.
  - Luce Foundation Civil Society Project - China Trips, 1998 May; September 1998 (Box 21, Folder 210)
    Exploratory trips by Elizabeth Knup and Marilyn Beach, primarily with regard to the Environmental Protection project. Includes brochures on Changchun.
  - Luce Foundation Civil Society Project - Marilyn Beach Correspondence, 1998 September (Box 21, Folder 211)
    Email correspondence from China concerning visit to Guizhou and planning for environmental projects in Harbin and possible flood-related project.
  - Luce Foundation Civil Society Project - Report on 1999 Activities, 2000 January (Box 22, Folder 212)
    Report and attachments
  - Luce Foundation Civil Society Project - Environmental Protection in Northeast China Working Group (General), 1998-2000 (Box 22, Folder 213)
    Includes background articles; information on environmental measures in Harbin.
  - Luce Foundation Civil Society Project - Environmental Protection in Northeast China Working Group (General), 1998-2000; Oversized map separated from folder. (Box 22, Folder 214)
    Contacts, planning, and notes for flood symposium and working group meeting.
    - Luce Foundation Civil Society Project - Environmental Protection in Northeast China Working Group (General), 1998-1999 (Folder 1)
      Unidentified map of China or Provinces.
  - Luce Foundation Civil Society Project - Environmental Protection in Northeast China Working Group (General), 1999-2000 (Box 22, Folder 215)
    Original folder labeled "Deng Wei." Includes a small amount of correspondence with Deng, but most contents are general.
  - Luce Foundation Civil Society Project - Sino-American Expert Working Group for Friendly Exchange on Ecological and Environmental Protection in the Northeast Region of China, 1995; 1997-1999 (Box 22, Folder 216)
    Includes report on working group meeting, May 19-25, 1999, and itinerary for Working Group U. S. Study Tour, November 6-21, 1999.
  - Luce Foundation Civil Society Project - Flood Symposium, 1999 May 10-15 (Box 22, Folder 217)
    Sino-U.S. Symposium on Ecosystem Recovery and Restoration in Disaster Areas in Heilongjiang Province.
  - Luce Foundation Civil Society Project - Environmental Protection in Northeast China, First Working Group Meeting, 1999 May 19-25 (Box 22, Folder 218)
    Joint Working Group for Civil Society Project, Decentralization of Local Environmental Protection. Includes trip report.
  - Luce Foundation Civil Society Project - Wetlands Survey, 2000 June 26 - July 4 (Box 22, Folder 219)
    Joint survey and technical exchange program.
  - Luce Foundation Civil Society Project - Environmental Protection in Northeast China, Third Working Group Meeting (Planning), 2000 July 6-11 (Box 22, Folder 220)
  - Luce Foundation Civil Society Project - Environmental Protection in Northeast China - Recruiting, 1995-1999 (Box 22, Folder 221)
  - Luce Foundation Civil Society Project - Environmental Protection Working Group - U. S. Participants, 1999-2000 (Box 22, Folder 222)
    William Chang, Francesca Di Cosmo, James Harris, Donald Woodward (participant in Post-Flood Ecosystem Recovery Workshop, May 10-15, 1999).
  - Luce Foundation Civil Society Project - Environmental Protection Working Group - Papers in Chinese (1 of 2), 1999-2000 (Box 22, Folder 223)
  - Luce Foundation Civil Society Project - Environmental Protection Working Group - Papers in Chinese (2 of 2), 1999-2000 (Box 23, Folder 224)
  - Luce Foundation Civil Society Project -Privatization of Education in Guizhou Working Group (General), 1998-2001 (Box 23, Folder 225)
    Project descriptions, planning, budget, articles, and correspondence. Notes on Guizhou team visit to U.S., May 15-30, 2000; report on Social Strength Schools in Guizhou Province, October 1999.
  - Luce Foundation Civil Society Project -Privatization of Education in Guizhou Working Group - Marilyn Beach Correspondence, 1998-2000 (Box 23, Folder 226)
  - Luce Foundation Civil Society Project -Privatization of Education in Guizhou Working Group Meeting, 1999 August 6-17; Still Image: 5x7 color print (Box 23, Folder 227)
    First working group meeting, in Guizhou. Includes one group photo of delegation with a Chinese band.
  - Luce Foundation Civil Society Project - Guizhou Papers (in Chinese), 1999 (Box 23, Folder 228)
  - Luce Foundation Civil Society Project - International Private Education Conference (Beijing), 1999 October 13-15 (Box 23, Folder 229)
    International Conference on Private Schools towards the 21st Century.
  - Luce Foundation Civil Society Project - Privatization of Education Working Group - U. S. Participants, 1999-2000 (Box 23, Folder 230)
    Dan Branham, Frank Kincaid, Robert Nelson
  - Luce Foundation Civil Society Project- Privatization of Education Working Group - Daniel Wright, 1997-1999 (Box 23, Folder 231)
    Correspondence file.
  - Speakers and Contacts Card File (Box 24, Folder 233)
    Alphabetical and Geographic files. Cards indicate names of China experts and potential speakers and include affiliation, interests, publications, and occasionally comments on qualifications and speaking ability. Cards were received out of order and have been resorted; the arrangement may not fully reflect the original order. Duplicate cards have been discarded from the alphabetical file.
  - Freeman Foundation Grant - Reports and Financial Statements, 1995-1998 (Box 51, Folder 500)
    A three-year grant from the Freeman Foundation supported NCUSCR projects to enhance knowledge of China among American Leaders. File maintained by Program Director Elizabeth Knup.
  - Freeman Foundation Grant - Congressional Travel Press Coverage, 1997 (Box 51, Folder 501)
  - Scholar Orientation Program - General, 1989-1997 (Box 53, Folder 525)
    Includes readings, 1990 correspondence, and form mailings.
  - Scholar Orientation Program - General (Various documents), undated; Special Format: Digital Media - 3.5" floppy disk
    Various SOP documents (listed on disk label), including NAFSA (National Association of Foreign Student Advisors).
    Access copy currently unavailable. Please contact an RAC archivist for further instruction.
  - Scholar Orientation Program - General (COP and SOP 64-67), 1994; Special Format: Digital Media - 3.5" floppy disk
    Consular Orientation Program (SOP no. 64); 1994 SOP Host Information; SOP nos. 65-67.
  - Scholar Orientation Program - General (SOP nos. 71-73), 1995; Special Format: Digital Media - 3.5" floppy disk
  - Scholar Orientation Program - General (COP no. 74, ACLS - SOP no. 76), 1997; Special Format: Digital Media - 3.5" floppy disk
    COP no. 74, 1997 March 23 - April 15; ACLS - SOP no. 76, 1997 June 29 - July 12.
  - Scholar Orientation Program - General (SOP Reunions), 1995-1996; Special Format: Digital Media - 3.5" floppy disk
    SOP Reunions: 1995 Attempt (63 files); 1996 Actual (14 files).
  - Scholar Orientation Program - General (SOP nos. 1-59), 1980 - circa 1992; Special Format: Digital Media - 3.5" floppy disk
    SOP - 715 names. Latest for updates. SOP 1-59.
  - Scholar Orientation Program - General (SOP nos. 60-67), 1993-1994; Special Format: Digital Media - 3.5" floppy disk
    SOP2. DTF. SOP nos. 60-67, Database Entry. (SOP 64 was a Consular Orientation Program).
  - Scholar Orientation Program - General (SOP 715), undated; Special Format: Digital Media - 3.5" floppy disk
    Disk labeled only "SOP 715."
  - Scholar Orientation Program - General (SOP. DTF, SOP2. DTF), undated; Special Format: Digital Media - 3.5" floppy disk
  - Scholar Orientation Program - General (SOP Itineraries - Backup), undated; Special Format: Digital Media - 3.5" floppy disk
  - Scholar Orientation Program - General (SOP Namelists and Host Families - Backup), undated; Special Format: Digital Media - 3.5" floppy disk
  - Scholar Orientation Program - General, 1984-1992 (Box 53, Folder 526)
    Participant lists, correspondence, and general materials for various SOP programs.
  - Scholar Orientation Program (No. 60, Journalism), 1993 May 16-29 (Box 53, Folder 527)
  - Scholar Orientation Program (No. 61, International Relations), 1993 June 17-30 (Box 53, Folder 528)
  - Scholar Orientation Program (No. 62, English Language and Literature), 1993 July 22 - August 4 (Box 53, Folder 529)
  - Scholar Orientation Program (No. 63, Economics), 1993 August 19 - September 1 (Box 54, Folder 530)
  - Consular Orientation Program (COP) ( SOP No. 64), 1994 February 24 - March 10 (Box 54, Folder 531)
  - Scholar Orientation Program (No. 65, Journalism), 1994 May 12-25 (Box 54, Folder 532)
  - Scholar Orientation Program (No. 66, English Language and Literature), 1994 June 4-16 (Box 54, Folder 533)
  - Scholar Orientation Program (No. 67, International Relations, Economics, and Law), 1994 July 7-20 (Box 54, Folder 534)
  - Scholar Orientation Program (No. 68, Economics, Law, and Management), 1995 June 11-24 (Box 54, Folder 535)
  - Scholar Orientation Program (No. 69, English Language and Literature), 1995 July 9-22 (Box 54, Folder 536)
  - Scholar Orientation Program (No. 70, International Relations and American Studies), 1995 August 13-26 (Box 55, Folder 537)
  - Consular Orientation Program (SOP No. 74), 1997 March 23 - April 5 (Box 55, Folder 538)
  - Teacher Orientation Program (No. (77), Education and American Studies), 1998 June 28 - July 11 (Box 55, Folder 539)
  - Scholar Orientation Program - Announcements and General Program Correspondence, 1984-1996 (Box 55, Folder 540)
    File consists mainly of announcements and inquiries for 1996 programs. Also includes notes on program planning for 1996.
  - Scholar Orientation Program - Alumni Survey and Reunion, 1992-1994 (Box 55, Folder 541)
  - Scholar Orientation Program - Host Families, 1980-1992; 1996-1997 (Box 55, Folder 542)
    Host Family Lists, 1980-1992; Mailings and Background Information for Host Families, 1996-1997.
  - Scholar Orientation Program - Readings and Background Materials, 1957-1997 (Box 55, Folder 543)
  - Scholar Orientation Program - Background Readings (in Chinese), Undated (Box 55, Folder 544)
  - Scholar Orientation Program - Possible Program Ideas, circa 1992 (Box 56, Folder 545 - 546)
  - Scholar Orientation Program - Visits and Program Planning (General), 1991-1996 (Box 56, Folder 547)
    Includes American Civil Liberties Union (PA), CARE, Sierra Club (PA), Planned Parenthood (PA and NYC), and Women's Organizations.
  - Scholar Orientation Program - Visits and Background Material (U.S. Government Agencies and Policies), 1987-1992 (Box 56, Folder 548)
    U.S. Department of Commerce, U. S. International Trade Commission, U. S. State Department, U. S. Information Agency (USIA), Voice of America, Federal Reserve Board, National Archives, Library of Congress.
  - Scholar Orientation Program - Visits and Background Readings (African American Issues), 1981-1992; 1995 (Box 56, Folder 549)
    Hampton University, Schomburg Center; Bibliography of African American Literature and readings sent by Farah Jasmine Griffin, University of Pennsylvania, 1995.
  - Scholar Orientation Program - Visits and Program Planning (New York), 1981-1997 (Box 56, Folder 550 - 551)
    Files consists mainly of pamphlets and brochures. Girl Scouts of the U.S.A., New York City Police Department, New York Public LIbrary, Merrill Lynch (in Chinese). New York Times, City Harvest, Federal Reserve Bank of New York, Port Authority; Introduction to the New York Stock Exchange, by Ben Wang, 1981 (in Chinese).
  - Scholar Orientation Program - New York Visits (Literary Assistance Center), 1996 (Box 56, Folder 552)
  - Scholar Orientation Program - Program Planning and Ideas (Philadelphia), 1994-1995 (Box 57, Folder 553)
  - Scholar Orientation Program - California (Background and Planning), 1997 (Box 57, Folder 554)
    Background materials and planning for a West Coast SOP.
  - Scholar Orientation Program - Military Information and Visit Sites, 1997 (Box 57, Folder 555)
  - Scholar Orientation Program - Arms Control and the Military (Background Information), 1989-1997 (Box 57, Folder 556-557)
  - Speakers File, circa 1970-1971 (Box 59, Folder 572)
  - Separated Oversized Material (Box 65)
- Ping Pong Diplomacy, 1971-2011; 9; 1.39 Cubic Feet 4 containers
  The Ping Pong Diplomacy series in RG 9 contains correspondence files for the members of the Joint Committee (NCUSCR and the U.S. Table Tennis Association) handling arrangements for the April 1972 visit to the U. S. of the Chinese Table Tennis Delegation. Materials also include planning, public relations, and fundraising correspondence; press and publicity kits; files on various cities on the tour itinerary; and photographs of the Chinese team's sightseeing and other visits
  - American Table Tennis Delegation to China, 1971 (Box 47, Folder 446)
  - Chinese Table Tennis Delegation Visit - General, 1971-1972 (Box 47, Folder 447)
    Background and planning, schedules, correspondence and addresses with the Chinese, press releases.
  - Chinese Table Tennis Delegation Visit - Background and Planning, Joint Committee, 1971-1973 (Box 47, Folder 448)
    Includes Auditor's Report.
  - Chinese Table Tennis Delegation Visit - Preston Schoyer Correspondence, 1971-1972 (Box 47, Folder 449)
  - Chinese Table Tennis Delegation Visit - Carl F. Stover Correspondence, 1971-1972 July (Box 47, Folder 450-451)
  - Chinese Table Tennis Delegation Visit - Alexander Eckstein Correspondence, 1971-1972 (Box 47, Folder 452)
  - Chinese Table Tennis Delegation Visit - Robert W. Gilmore Correspondence, 1971-1972 (Box 47, Folder 453)
  - Chinese Table Tennis Delegation Visit - Graham B. Steenhoven Correspondence, 1971-1972 (Box 47, Folder 454)
  - Chinese Table Tennis Delegation Visit - J. Rufford Harrison Correspondence, 1971-1972; 1998 (Box 47, Folder 455)
    Harrison was chair of the U. S. Table Tennis Association's International Committee.
  - Chinese Table Tennis Delegation Visit - Osgood Nichols Associates, Inc., 1971-1972 (Box 47, Folder 456)
    Public relations.
  - Chinese Table Tennis Delegation Visit - Fundraising Letters, 1971-1972 (Box 47, Folder 457)
  - Chinese Table Tennis Delegation Visit - Instruction and Guide for the PRC Visit, 1972 (Box 48, Folder 458)
    Notebook prepared by the National Committee. Removed from ring binder.
  - Chinese Table Tennis Delegation Visit - Press Information, 1971-1972 (Box 48, Folder 459)
    File includes schedules and itineraries, memos, press lists, press releases, and some
  - Chinese Table Tennis Delegation Visit - Press Kit, 1972 (Box 48, Folder 460)
    File also includes brochure from the 25th Anniversary celebration of the visit.
  - Chinese Table Tennis Delegation Visit - Detroit and Ann Arbor, 1972 April (Box 48, Folder 461)
  - Chinese Table Tennis Delegation Visit - Washington, DC, 1972 April (Box 48, Folder 462)
    Includes Williamsburg, VA, and Maryland.
  - Chinese Table Tennis Delegation Visit - New York (Itineraries), 1972 April (Box 48, Folder 463)
    Including detailed itinerary for New York City visit; Room Assignments
  - Chinese Table Tennis Delegation Visit - Memphis (Press Coverage), 1972 April; Still Image: Black and white 8x10 glossy print. (Box 48, Folder 464)
    Includes program and photo of Chinese player receiving award paddle.
  - Chinese Table Tennis Delegation Visit - Memphis Publicity Kit, 1972 (Box 48, Folder 465)
    Memphis Area Chamber of Commerce packet.
  - Chinese Table Tennis Delegation Visit - Los Angeles and San Francisco, 1972 April (Box 48, Folder 466)
  - Chinese Table Tennis Delegation Visit - Photographs, 1972 April; Still Images: Black-and-white and color, 3x5 - 11x14 prints. Two 4x6 negatives. Oversized photos and negative separated to box 64. (Box 48, Folder 467)
    Publicity and candid photos of delegation visits to New York, Washington, DC, Memphis, Los Angeles, and Stanford. Arrival of Delegation and White House visit; team roster.
  - Chinese Table Tennis Delegation Visit - Follow-Up, 1972-1973; 1990; 1998; 2001; 2011 (Box 48, Folder 468)
    Includes copy of Ruth Eckstein, "Ping Pong Diplomacy: A View from behind the Scenes" (1990); letter from Zheng Minzhi (1998).
  - Ping Pong Diplomacy - Twenty-Fifth Anniversary (United Nations Program), 1997 July 24 (Box 48, Folder 469)
  - Separated Oversized Material (Box 64)
    Oversized photos separated from Chinese Table Tennis Delegation Visit, 1972 April, box 48, folder 467.
  - Separated Oversized Material (Box 65)
- Development, 1972-2006; 10; 2.37 Cubic Feet 6 containers
  The Development series in RG 9 consists primarily of a set of Final Reports from the National Committee to the U. S. Information Agency and the U. S. Department of Education, 1982-1988, accounting for its administration of Fulbright and other federally funded exchange and education programs.
  - Fundraising (General), 1977-2004 (Box 51, Folder 502)
  - Potential Funding - Kimsey Foundation, 2001 (Box 51, Folder 503)
  - Meeting with Foundation Officials concerning Medicine and Public Health in China, 1972 May 5 (Box 51, Folder 504)
    Luncheon meeting, hosted by the Josiah Macy Foundation.
  - Meeting with Foundation Officials concerning Exchanges with China, 1972 November 17 (Box 52, Folder 505)
    Meeting concerning development of and prospects for scholarly, educational, and cultural exchanges with China (and potential funding for such exchanges).
  - Final Report to the United States Information Agency on Grant IA-19885-19-G, 1981 April - 1982 December (Box 57, Folder 558-559)
    Reports on USIA and United States Department of Education Projects.
  - Final Report to the United States Information Agency and United States Education Department on Grant IA -20397-19-G, 1982 August - 1984 December (Box 58, Folder 560)
  - Final Report to the U.S. Information Agency and the U.S. Department of Education on Grant IA -20483-19-G, 1982 October - 1985 June (Box 58, Folder 561-562)
    Financial Reports, Private Sector Program (USIA), Center for International Education (USED), Office of Educational Research and Improvement (USED).
  - Final Report to the U.S. Information Agency and the U. S. Department of Education on Grant IA-21143-19-G, 1984 February 15 - 1985 July 31 (Box 58, Folder 563)
    Financial Reports, Private Sector Programs (USIA), Center for International Education (USED).
  - Final Report to the U.S. Information Agency and the U. S. Department of Education on Grant IA-21733-19-G, 1985 February 15 - 1986 May 31 (Box 58, Folder 564)
    Financial Reports, Private Sector Programs (USIA - exchanges to the U. S., Scholar Orientation Programs, and Facilitative Assistance), Center for International Education (USED - Provincial Educators and Campus Designers to the U.S., Summer Seminar to China).
  - Final Report to the U.S. Information Agency and the U. S. Department of Education on Grant IA-22445-19-G, 1986 February 1 - 1988 March 31 (Box 58, Folder 565-566)
    Financial Reports, Private Sector Program (USIA), Center for International Education (USED). Report includes narrative reports, itineraries, name lists, and contribution lists for grant-funded delegations and programs. Report split between two binders, labeled part 1 and part 2.
  - Final Report to the U.S. Information Agency and the U. S. Department of Education on Grant IA-PSMA-G7192902, 1987 March 1 - 1988 June 30 (Box 58, Folder 567-568)
    Financial Reports, Private Sector Program (USIA), Center for International Education (USED). Report includes narrative reports, itineraries, name lists, and contribution lists for grant-funded delegations and programs. Report split between two binders, labeled (part 1) and part 2.
  - NCUSCR Final Report to the U.S. Information Agency on Grant IA-PSMA-G8193142, 1988 (Box 59, Folder 569-570)
    Report lacks cover sheets, but includes narrative reports, itineraries, name lists, and contribution lists for grant-funded delegations and programs. Report split into two binders.
  - Sample Funders Reports, 1990; 1994 (Box 59, Folder 571)
    Report on the Study Delegation on U. S. History and Culture from the PRC, 1990 July 1-28, 1990; Workshop on the Development of a Modern Banking System - China Trip Report, 1994 May 30 - June 10.
  - Proposed Project on Distance Learning for Workforce Development, circa 2003 (Box 61, Folder 594)
    Draft budget for proposed delegation to China.
  - Grant and Contract Budget Reports, 2006 (Box 61, Folder 595)
    Report through June 30, 2006. Various pages of General Ledger Detail, October 2005 - June 2006, were discarded in processing.
- Board of Directors, Committees, and Members records, 1965-2012; 11; 3.04 Cubic Feet 8 containers
  The Board of Directors, Committees, and Members Files series in RG 9 includes signficant early organizational and program documents, along with files specifically designated as "historical." Other records include the NCUSCR Bylaws and successive revisions; a file of National Committee press releases, 1973-1998; various membership files; acknowledgements of contributions, 1974-1979; and search committee records, 1997-2001.
  - National Committee History, 1965-1967; Still Images: 7 black and white prints (5x7 and 3x5). (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Includes professional photos of unidentified meeting (photos by Paul S. Buck); Draft Perspectus of the National Committee, undated; Development Committee minutes, September (6),1966; Robert Mang, Confidential program memo, August 26, 1966; Program Subcommittee minutes, May 17, 1967.
  - National Committee in the News, 1966-1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Clippings on the National Committee's formation and launching.
  - NCUSCR Statement of Purpose, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Statement of Non-Governmental Status, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Addressed to the Office of Public Information at the United Nations.
  - New York Meeting, 1965 December 9 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Meeting to Consider Formation of National Committee, 1966 January 14 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "West Coast Organizing Group" Meeting, 1966 May 25 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Press Release, 1966 June 7 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Announcing formation of the National Committee.
  - Meeting at Stock Exchange Club, San Francisco, 1966 June 29 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - National Committee Luncheon (Fairmont Hotel), 1966 October 21 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Prospectus, circa 1966 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - General Correspondence, 1966 October 20; 1967 February - June (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Folder mislabeled "AFSC China Sub Committee." Correspondence with Cecil Thomas, Pamela Mang, Robert Scalapino, and others, concerning membership, foundation support, and other concerns.
  - Press Release, 1967 June 6 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Announcing NCUSCR program plans and purposes on receipt of grants from the Ford Foundation and the Rockefeller Brothers Fund.
  - Press Release, 1968 July 8 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Announcing election of A. Doak Barnett as Board chair.
  - Past Program Proposals, 1965-1967 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Proposals, memos, correspondence, and observations concerning National Committee programs and planning. Includes drafts prepared for program and development committee meetings, and memos on general and specific programs.
  - Program Survey, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    "Program survey of our first six months," January 1967; reports on seminar program and other program outlines.